Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
Why are you here?
你怎么会在这里？
I'm 18 now.
我已经十八岁了
No matter who is against it,
这次不管谁反对
I will come see you.
我都会来见你
Never come again.
你别再来了
If you come here,
你如果来这里
I'll have to move away.
我就得搬走了
I have students I care about here.
我还有重要的学生们
Never come again.
你不要再来了
-Mr. Nogami. -Yes?
-野上老师 -是
If you would have me, maybe we could get to know each other
如果你愿意接受我 也许我们可以慢慢互相了解
a little bit at a time.
请多指教
Yes!
是！
I would be honored!
我才是 请多指教！
Why?
为什么？
It has been a while.
好久不见了
You seem well.
你看起来过得很好
Um, what are--
请问你今天…
Did Akira come?
阿晶他来过了吗？
Did he come here to see you?
他有跑来这里见你吗？
Yes.
是的
Just once.
只有一次
But he left right away.
不过他立刻就走了
I don't think he'll be coming back again.
我想他应该不会再来了
I'm terribly sorry.
实在非常抱歉
I'm sure he was a bother.
他给你添麻烦了吧
I'm not sure how much you all know,
我不知道大家了解多少
but even after that scandal,
即使引发那种风波
to find out that you are still teaching.
发现你还是继续当老师
I have to say, I was surprised.
我觉得真是不可思议
But I'm sure it took a lot to return to work,
想必是有相当大的觉悟
so you must be a good teacher.
你一定是个好老师
Excuse me. May I say something.
不好意思 我能插句话吗？
I'm her colleague Nogami.
我是她同事 我叫野上
I'm currently dating Ms. Suenaga.
我们现在正在交往
So I don't believe you need to worry about your son.
因此您应该不用担心您儿子的事
I see, you have a partner.
原来你有对象啊
For us,
我们倒是
the incident from three years ago
因为三年前的事
caused us to live separately,
现在母子分开住
and the time we have as a family
等于是失去了
has been as good as ruined.
一家人相处的时间
But you…
可是老师你…
You haven't lost anything.
却什么都没失去
I'm sorry for dropping by.
抱歉突然打扰
May you have a good life.
祝你们幸福
OCTOBER 23, TUESDAY
（10月23日 星期二）
HIJIRI, I WANT TO SEE YOU. KUROIWA.
（小圣 我想见你）
Never come again.
你别再来了
If you come here,
你如果来这里
I'll have to move away.
我就得搬走了
The booklet Ms. Suenaga is handing out
现在末永老师发下去的册子
shows you how to make the props and costumes for the recital.
上面有写发表会用的服装 跟小道具的作法
-Show it to your parents at home. -Okay.
-请记得拿给家长看 -好
They took her away!
他们带走她了！
My parents sent a car and took Ayano away!
刚才父母家有人开车来 把彩乃带走了！
-Costume? -Yes, for a fairy.
-戏服？ -是的 精灵的戏服
MIMI AND THE RAINBOW FOREST
（《咪咪和彩虹森林》）
Here.
给
Is that something you can do?
你能帮她准备吗？
For Ayano.
为了彩乃
Um…
嗯…
Please come to the recital.
请你一定要来发表会
We don't want things this way either!
我们也不想事情发展成这种地步！
So take these small steps to prove to them that you're needed,
正因为这样 才要一点一滴 让大家知道彩乃仍需要母亲
and earn your parents' trust back.
重新赢得你父母的信任
Then you'll be able to be
希望能让你
reunited with Ayano again.
再次跟彩乃一起生活
Please do this.
戏服就麻烦你了
It will make Ayano happy.
彩乃肯定会很高兴
MIMI AND THE RAINBOW FOREST
（《咪咪和彩虹森林》）
What's with that woman?
那女人搞什么东西？
Excuse me.
不好意思
You knew Ms. Suenaga from her old school?
您是末永老师前一所学校的家长吗？
She's been treating my daughter well.
现在我家孩子深受老师关照
She used to teach junior high, right?
我记得她以前是初中老师吧？
HIJIRI SUENAGA KOBOSHI JUNIOR HIGH
（末永圣 子星初中）
DISAPPEARS AFTER A RUMORED AFFAIR WITH STUDENT
（疑似与学生有淫秽行为后消失）
KOMIYA DAI-ICHI ELEMENTARY
（小宫第一小学）
Everyone's gotten so much better with their lines.
大家越来越熟悉台词了
Now we should focus on the parts without lines.
接下来我们就思考 没台词时该做什么动作
Yes.
是啊
Why don't we do a run through.
要不要从头演一次试看看？
-Good idea. -Okay.
-好主意 -好的
Good morning.
早上好
Good…
早…
Huh?
嗯？
Why?
为什么？
Hijiri, the parents are all here.
圣 家长们都过来了
They want to speak with you.
他们说要和你谈谈
What is this about?
这是怎么回事？
Ms. Suenaga, I'll just come out and ask.
末永老师 我就开门见山地问了
Were you involved in a case of sexual misconduct?
听说你以前曾犯下淫行 是真的吗？
Someone said they saw that child's mother come complain to the school.
有人看到那位同学的家长 跑到学校来投诉
Who did?
是谁说的？
I did.
是我
Something seemed really off, so I got curious and read some articles.
我感觉不太对劲 有些好奇 就去查了网路上的留言
They said that three years ago,
他们说三年前
you messed around with your middle school student
你对初中的学生出手
You were chasing that boy around.
你好像一直在纠缠那位学生
Running off alone in the school, often sneaking away together.
在学校两人独处 经常偷偷一起溜走
Then you had to suddenly quit because you got pregnant or something.
你会突然辞职也是因为怀孕还是什么
It's so surprising.
真是惊人
People aren't always as they seem.
真是人不可貌相啊
After hearing that,
听到这种传言
we thought it needed to be addressed directly.
我们决定要过来问个清楚
Ms. Suenaga, do you admit to being
你承认自己是
a sexual predator?
淫秽教师吗？
I…
我…
That is ridiculous.
胡说八道
I've known her a long time, but I've never heard such rumors,
我认识她很久了 但我从没听说过这件事
nor are they true.
也与事实有出入
Spreading around such gossip,
胡乱散播谣言
attacking her personally, won't bring Ayano back.
就算你对她做人身攻击 彩乃也不会回到你身边
Don't run from your own problems.
请不要逃避你自己的问题
This isn't--
那根本不是…
If something happens, please call me anytime.
如果有什么事 请随时联络我
I will do my best to listen.
我会尽可能倾听
Right, Ayano is with her grandparents now, I heard.
对了 我听说 彩乃现在好像住在爷爷奶奶家
-That's why she did this? -No.
-所以才闹这一出吗？ -不是的
More importantly, the school recital is coming up.
话说回来 马上就是学校发表会了
Your children are working very hard.
孩子们都很认真练习
Please continue to watch over them.
请大家温暖地守护他们吧
Of course, we'll send them over right away.
当然 我马上让孩子来学校
I'll call the other mothers to explain.
我也去联络其他妈妈和她们解释
I'm so sorry, Ms. Suenaga.
老师 真是对不起
After you.
请吧
Stop with that face.
又露出这种表情
You would've just confused the situation with the truth.
你只会让事态和事实更混乱
There's no need to talk about that incident anymore.
事到如今 你不需要再针对那件事解释什么了
Just ignore them from now on.
以后都无视就好
But now
但现在
Ms. Tachibana is getting blamed.
橘太太好像反而因此受到责怪
It's not like everything she said was baseless and untrue.
她说的也并不全是假的
But some of that stuff was totally malicious.
可是有些根本是恶意的谎言
You mentioned before
之前你说过吧？
that you want to spend your life teaching here.
你想一直在这里当老师
That it was your wish.
你说这就是你的愿望
Then get it together.
所以你要振作一点
Just focus on what you need to do as a teacher now.
你只要思考现在身为老师该做什么
MIMI AND THE RAINBOW FOREST
（《咪咪和彩虹森林》）
KOMIYA DAI-ICHI ELEMENTARY
（小宫第一小学）
Ayano!
彩乃！
I'm so glad to see you today!
今天能见到你真是太好了！
I heard you're going to be a fairy for the recital.
发表会的这个 听说你要演精灵呀
Should I make your costume?
妈妈帮你准备衣服吧？
Ayano?
彩乃？
Wait, Ayano!
等一下 彩乃
I already thought I'd add your favorite pink flowers--
妈妈想好了 就加上你最喜欢的粉红色花朵…
It's fine!
不用了！
I'm having Grandma do it.
我会叫奶奶帮我准备
You talked bad about Ms. Hijiri, didn't you?
妈妈 你对大家说了 圣老师的坏话 对吧？
Said mean things?
你说了很过分的话吧？
I hate you for that.
我最讨厌这样的妈妈了
What?
什么？
Want to say something?
你想说什么？
I feel like an idiot!
我就像个白痴一样
MIMI AND THE RAINBOW FOREST
（《咪咪和彩虹森林》）
KOJI WATANABE IS GETTING MARRIED!
（恭喜渡边浩二结婚大喜！）
Did you read it?
你看了吗？
What a surprise.
真是让人吓一跳
I mean, I'd like to go to the reception,
那个 虽然我很想参加婚礼
but I'm so busy I'm probably not going to make it.
可是现在工作太忙 大概没办法去
Could you give them my gift?
你可以帮我把礼物交给他们吗？
Yeah, sure, of course.
当然可以
Thanks.
谢谢你
By the way, I've been meaning to tell you,
还有 圣 我一直想找时间告诉你
I'm actually
其实我现在
dating someone.
有交往的对象
What?
什么？
You've met her before.
你也见过她
What? I have?
什么？我也见过吗？
Ms. Haraguchi.
是原口小姐
That Ms. Haraguchi?
那个原口小姐吗？
Capable, enigmatic and hard to pin-down.
既优秀又神秘 捉摸不定
I feel like she's always testing me.
感觉她好像时时刻刻都在试探我
Testing you?
试探你？
She's not like you at all.
她跟你完全不一样
Well, I'm not sure you needed to add that.
跟我完全不一样这句是多余的
I didn't mean anything by it.
我没有特别的意思
You must like her.
你很喜欢她吧
Just being with her
现在能跟她在一起
is more than enough.
我就非常满足了
Congratulations.
恭喜你
Thanks, Hijiri.
谢谢你 圣
Kuroiwa!
黑岩！
Do you like me?
你喜欢我吗？
Even just a little?
即使只有一点点？
-Here you go. -Yay!
-久等了 -好耶！
It's their limited time only, Berry Special Pancake.
他们期间限定的莓果特制松饼
Looks so good.
感觉好好吃
Ice cream.
冰淇淋
Yummy!
好吃！
Why are all the best dishes only offered for a limited time?
为什么好吃的东西几乎都是限定品？
Here.
来
What's with you?
你怎么了？
You haven't said a word.
一句话都不说
Totally ruining the vibes.
气氛都搞砸了
I'm a little rattled.
我现在很混乱
I saw Ms. Suenaga.
我见到老师了
-No. -She hadn't changed.
-我不想听 -她完全没变
I realized my feelings hadn't either.
我发现我对她的感情也没变
What did Suenaga say?
末永她说了什么？
Never to come again.
她叫我别再去找她
Then stay with me.
那和我在一起吧
I'm sorry.
抱歉
I can't treat you the way you should be treated.
我无法好好珍惜你
Stop it with that.
不要说这种话
Even if it's devious and unfair,
不管是狡猾还是不公平
some people don't care as long as they're together.
有的人只要能在一起就满足了
You're smart, it's okay to take advantage of this.
你脑袋这么好 应该多耍点小聪明呀
Let's end this.
到此为止吧
I'm sorry.
抱歉
No.
不要
I'm not breaking up.
我不要分手
You're the one who's wrong.
错的人是你
I'll never break up.
我绝对不会分手
AIKO KUROIWA
（黑岩爱子）
One chicken stew.
一碗鸡汤
There's no need to talk about that incident anymore.
事到如今 你不需要再针对那件事解释什么了
Just ignore them from now on.
以后都无视就好
Delivery.
有您的信
Here you go.
请收下
KOSUKE SHIMAZAKI
（岛崎康介）
There's something I haven't told you.
我有事情没告诉你
Your father left when you were five.
你爸在你五岁时离家了
Your school contacted me.
你的学校通知我
You missed two days of school last week.
他们说你上周只去了三天
Why?
为什么？
And your career path.
还有未来志愿
You decided to skip college to go into the workforce?
你好像不打算升学 要直接工作？
I was surprised too.
我也吓了一大跳
Akira.
阿晶
You have great grades.
你的成绩很好
You're also in the advanced classes.
而且还进了资优班
It's such a waste.
太可惜了
Is there something you want to do?
你有什么想做的事吗？
I want to be independent.
我想赶快独立
What?
什么？
I can attend school part-time while working.
我可以边打工边上学
which would help our finances.
那样经济方面也比较轻松
-I just want to work. -Is it for her?
-总之我想先找份工作 -是为了她吗？
You want to hurry up and be equal
你想赶快跟她变成对等关系
so you can be with her?
为了能和她在一起？
I met Ms. Suenaga the other day.
上次我去见过老师了
She said you saw her.
因为她说你去见她了
-I can't believe-- -I know, I'm sorry.
-你又擅自这么做… -没错 对不起
Was I worried for nothing?
是我多操心了吗？
Ms. Suenaga is dating someone who works at her school.
末永老师在她的学校也有了新对象
He even told me I don't need to worry about you coming around again.
对方也说完全不需要担心 你会再去和她见面
So
所以
if it has nothing to do with her,
若是跟老师没有任何关系
then can you tell me why you want to work
那你可以和我说是为了什么去工作
and what kind of person
你想成为怎么样的社会人士
you want to be?
好好思考一下吧
Okay.
好的
I'll decide myself and take responsibility.
我会自己决定 自己负责
Akira! Hey!
阿晶！喂！
What am I supposed to do?
我到底该怎么做？
TO AIKO KUROIWA
（致黑岩爱子）
BECAUSE I'M HIS FATHER
（正因为我是父亲）
I'M COMING BACK I WANT TO SPEAK TO HIM
（我会回来跟阿晶说说话）
I'LL BE WORKING IN YAMAEJIMA.
（我在山江岛工作）
TOKYO
（东京）
-Kawai. -Yes?
-川合 -是
Come with me.
过来
You might be getting sent overseas.
下次人事调动 你可能会调去海外
What?
什么？
An overseas assignment?
你是说派驻海外吗？
The chief is reviewing it.
部长正在审核
If you get it, we're all counting on you.
如果确定的话就拜托你啦
Am I being tested?
莫非你是在试探我吗？
What?
什么？
The overseas assignment.
派驻海外
Are you testing me to see
你想试探我看看
how I'll answer?
我会作出什么决定？
I see. Maybe I am testing you.
是吗？我可能是在试探你吧
I can't even tell myself anymore.
我自己也搞不太清楚
Is that what you think I'd say?
你认为我会说什么？
It's just a post for two years, three years maximum.
不过是两年 最长三年的岗位
Going will improve your future prospects.
如果去的话 肯定能提升你往后的前景
But a long-distance relationship won't work.
不过远距离恋爱行不通吧
So should we make a clean break to send you off without regrets?
所以我们应该干脆分手 爽快地送你出国吗？
But I mean, someone else might get chosen for the position.
但是 最后也有可能是选别人去
It wouldn't be fair of me to push for you too much.
一直支持你去好像也不公平
That's my dilemma.
很矛盾
Oh, I thought you were testing me.
什么啊 我还以为你是在试探我呢
Open this.
把这打开
Long-distance won't work?
远距离恋爱行不通的？
It's true that it didn't work with Hijiri.
跟圣那时也是因为这样
Which is why I've been thinking.
因此我一直都在考虑
Even if I get posted overseas,
即便我被派驻海外
I still want to be with you.
我也想跟你在一起
So
所以
if I go, I want to make us official.
如果我要去的话 想确定关系
-Huh? -So basically, marry me?
-什么？ -也就是说 我们结婚吧？
Get married and do what?
结婚之后怎样？
Ultimately, I don't care whether you come with me or not.
始终 我不管你会不会跟我去
We'd be married, so I wouldn't worry about being apart.
因为已经结婚了 所以分隔两地都不会太担心
In other words,
换句话说
we'd get married just to secure this relationship?
只是为了维持这段关系而特地结婚？
Let's get married.
结婚吧
You don't need to test us.
你不需要这样试探我们
We can be free
我们可以自在地
to love each other.
爱着彼此
Unlike with Hijiri.
跟小圣那时不同
Miwa.
美和
Ms. Tachibana.
橘小姐
BAR ICHIRIKI
（一力小酒馆）
-Are you okay? -I'm totally fine.
-你还好吗？ -我没事啊
We're almost there.
马上就到了
-I said I'm fine! -Huh? Ah!
-我都说了我没事！ -嗯？啊！
What?
什么？
What? Really?
骗人的吧？那个…
BARLEY TEA
（麦茶）
What is this about?
怎么回事？
You're acting awful nice.
突然这么温柔
Because we're the same?
因为我们是同类吗？
Because love makes you do crazy things too?
因为你也是一恋爱 就会脑袋失控的女人吗？
You want to be friends?
想跟我当朋友吗？
Answer me, Ms. Hijiri.
回答我 圣老师
You made the costume for Ayano!
原来你有帮彩乃做戏服！
Forget it, she doesn't want it.
算了 反正她也不要
No, don't!
不要 别丢！
I'm sure Ayano will love it!
彩乃一定会很喜欢！
I already told you…
我已经和你说了…
Please come to the school before the recital!
请在发表会开始前来学校！
-Let's give it to Ayano. -Leave it!
-把这个交给彩乃吧 -不要管了！
Just leave me alone!
不要再管我了！
It's no use anyway.
反正做了也没用！
She won't wear it even if I make it.
做了她也不会穿
She's never coming back.
彩乃再也不会回来了
No matter what I do, nothing will change!
无论我做什么 事情都不会有任何改变！
Even so,
即使如此
you should make the effort.
你仍然要努力去做
You should work to change your situation.
要努力去改善现状
What about you?
你自己呢？
Aren't you just running away?
你不也只是在逃避吗？
BAR ICHIRIKI
（一力小酒馆）
What are you doing here?
你在做什么？
I was looking for you.
我在找你
Then I stepped in a ditch.
结果不小心掉到水沟
I told you not to come.
我说过你不可以再来了
-Hey! -Please listen.
-喂！ -请你听我说
-I said no! -I found a letter when I got home.
-都说了不行！ -我回家后收到信…
Right now,
现在
I'm in hot water.
我惹上了麻烦
Because of what happened with you three years ago.
原因就是三年前跟你之间的事
Honestly, I'm in trouble.
老实说我很困扰
For me,
对我而言
all I have is teaching.
我只能当老师
Maybe I'm not suited to being a teacher like you said,
也许就像你说的 我不适合当老师
but this is all I have.
可是我只有这些
So please,
所以求求你
just leave me alone.
你别再跟我扯上关系了
And stay away!
别再来了！
Okay.
好的
You want to discard it.
你想要丢弃
Throw away your past, cutting off everything.
舍弃过去 切割一切
You think you can reinvent yourself somewhere new.
你以为能在新地方变成崭新的自己
But it's just an illusion.
但这只是个假象
I won't pretend
我不会假装
the past didn't happen.
当作过去从未发生
I can't.
我办不到
I won't forget because it's all precious to me.
我不会忘记 因为曾发生过的一切都很重要
I broke up with Iwasaki.
我跟岩崎分手了
But that's something I did on my own.
但这是我自己想这么做
Just how I forced everything three years ago.
就像三年前全部都是我强人所难
So don't worry about it,
所以你不用担心
and become a good teacher.
请当个好老师吧
Although, I'm not sure what kind of teacher that is…
虽然我不知道怎样才是好老师…
I'm a little disappointed.
我有点失望
Disappointed in you.
对你有点失望
I hate you for that.
我最讨厌这样的妈妈了
You should make the effort.
你仍然要努力去做
You should work to change your situation.
要努力去改善现状
KOMIYA DAI-ICHI ELEMENTARY
（小宫第一小学）
RECITAL
（学习发表会）
Next, the third and fourth graders present "Mimi and the Rainbow Forest."
接下来是三、四年级 演出的《咪咪和彩虹森林》
Such a nice day, Popo!
今天也很晴朗呢 波波！
Woof woof!
汪汪！
Such a nice day, but nothing ever changes.
虽然天气这么好 但每天都一成不变
A large tornado approaches Mimi and Popo.
巨大的龙卷风正朝着咪咪与波波接近
There's a tornado getting closer!
是龙卷风正在逐渐接近！
Let's get a closer look!
我们靠近一点看吧！
Look at this tree, the leaves are like rainbows!
你快看 这棵树的叶子就像彩虹一般！
This whole forest used to shimmer like a rainbow.
过去这整座森林 都像这样闪着彩虹光芒
What Mimi and Popo found
咪咪和波波发现的正是
was a magical rainbow tree displaying its true colors!
闪着七彩光芒的魔法彩虹树
Who are you?
你是谁？
I'm the Rainbow Forest fairy.
我是彩虹森林的精灵
I knew you would be coming.
我知道你们会来到这里
Do you know where the sword of courage is?
你知道勇气之剑在哪里吗？
Only the chosen one can find the sword of courage.
只有被选中的人才能找到勇气之剑
Stars sparkled in the night sky.
星星在夜空中闪耀光辉
Okay!
好的！
-Don't run! You'll bump into each other! -Ms. Tachibana, your mom's here.
-不要跑 会撞到人！ -橘同学 你妈妈有来喔
Ayano, I'm sorry I'm late.
彩乃 对不起 妈妈迟到了
I didn't make it in time.
我这个来不及做好
I had so much trouble getting the flower to look good.
这个花我一直做不好
I tried to make it in time.
我尽可能想赶上发表会
Sorry, I'm sure you don't want it now.
你已经不需要了吧 对不起
Look Ayano, I'll be going away for a little while.
妈妈会暂时不在家
I'll be doing my best to find a new job and home.
我会努力找到工作跟房子
So we can live together again.
希望我们能够再一起生活
What?
什么？
Take care.
你要保重
Be a good girl.
当个好孩子
They said
他们说
you're careless
你不检点
and a liar.
又爱说谎
Not to meet you.
叫我不能跟你见面
But
但是
I love you.
我最喜欢你了
So promise to come get me.
你一定要来接我
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
I'm sorry for all the trouble I caused
很抱歉给你添麻烦了
spreading baseless rumors.
因为散播了一些不实谣言
Throw away your past, cutting off everything.
舍弃过去 切割一切
You think you can reinvent yourself somewhere new.
你以为能在新地方变成崭新的自己
I'm a little disappointed.
我有点失望
Disappointed in you.
对你有点失望
Wait!
等等！
It's true.
是真的
That rumor
那则谣言
is true.
确实是真的
At my previous school,
我在之前的学校
I had an incident with a student.
跟学生之间出了问题
Then the rumors…?
这么说传言是…
She got pregnant?
她怀孕了？
That didn't happen!
那不是事实！
However,
但是
I can't make any excuses for what I did.
我无法为自己做的事找借口
At that time,
那时的我
I had inappropriate feelings for a male student.
对某位男同学产生了不该有的感情
Ms. Suenaga!
末永老师！
We also met alone.
也曾两人单独见面
Which is why
因此
I quit my former school.
我才辞去前一所学校的教职
Fortunately, this school gave me another chance.
幸好 这所学校给我一个机会
I wanted to continue to teach.
我才能继续当老师
I was afraid the rumors would spread, so I stayed quiet.
我很害怕谣言回传开 所以才隐瞒大家
For betraying all of you,
背叛大家的信任
I'm truly sorry.
实在非常抱歉
-Komiya Dai-Ichi Elementary. -We are currently investigating.
-这里是小宫第一小学 -我们正在调查这件事
What a mess!
真是一团糟！
This is going to be like a hornet's nest.
看来短时间内是难以收拾了
Ms. Niwa, you knew about this, didn't you?
丹羽老师 你应该早就知道这件事了吧？
-I wanted to give her a chance. -But sexual misconduct!
-我想给她一个重来的机会 -不过那可是淫行啊！
-In this day and age? -Right?
-发生在现今的社会？ -对吧？
I'm the one who approved it.
是我同意这件事的
Principal Aida!
校长！
I mean, at this stage,
不过既然事已至此
it would be best for Ms. Suenaga to explain things herself.
还是请末永老师亲自郑重说明比较好
Hijiri.
圣
They're asking you not to return to the classroom for now.
他们让你暂时别回课室教课
Until they make a decision,
直到他们做出决定前
you're on desk duty.
你就在教职员室帮忙处理事务
Okay.
是
I'm sorry.
非常抱歉
To end up like this after all of your help.
你们都那样帮我了 我却搞砸了
Why did you decide to tell them?
为什么要自己说出来？
Because I couldn't change.
这样下去我不会改变
By pretending it didn't happen,
把过去的事当成从未发生
running away, lying to myself,
不停地逃避 对自己说谎
nothing would change!
这样什么都不会改变！
I can't become a good teacher.
我不可能成为好老师
Not like this.
在这种状态下办不到
That's what I realized,
因为我这么觉得
so I told them.
所以才坦白一切
I'm not surprised.
我一点都不惊讶
But if this loses you your job, then it's all for nothing.
但因为这样待不下去 根本是赔了夫人又折兵
Ms. Suenaga is dating someone who works at her school.
末永老师在她的学校也有了新对象
I'm in hot water.
我惹上了麻烦
Because of what happened with you three years ago.
原因就是三年前跟你之间的事
All I have is teaching.
我只能当老师
Just leave me alone.
你别再跟我扯上关系了
There's food for you.
饭煮好了
Akira.
阿晶
Take a seat.
过来坐下
Sit.
坐下
Your work called me.
今天你打工的地方通知我
You've missed several days now.
他们说你已经请假好几天了
Plus you're skipping school?
学校也不去了？
What's going on?
你到底是怎么了？
I'm not going to college anyway.
反正我又不升学
-Wait. Time to cut the crap. -Ow.
-等一下 你闹够了吧 -好痛
I mean, what the hell?
你到底在搞什么？
What aren't you happy with?
你到底有什么不满？
To your mother who has been holding in her sadness at being apart from you,
对忍耐着伤心分开生活的妈妈
you barely spoke a word!
也不好好说上几句话！
What'd be the point?
说了有什么用？
You know, don't you?
你也知道吧？
What Mom did?
妈妈以前做的事
Your father left when you were five.
你爸在你五岁时离家了
Because he was struggling with work, right?
因为工作不顺利 对吧？
That's the reason I gave you for our divorce.
我跟你说是因为这样才离婚
But I
但我
fell in love with someone.
喜欢上别人了
She's one to talk after what she did,
她还敢说 自己明明
falling for a married man.
也爱上了有妇之夫
That's exactly why.
正因如此
She doesn't want you to make the same--
她才不想你再犯同样的…
Still! She doesn't tell me anything important.
就算是这样！ 她从不告诉我最重要的事
She kept Dad's letters from me.
还有爸爸寄来的信也收着
Then she tells me to suck it up and work hard? To forget!
她却叫我忍耐 叫我念书 叫我忘记
Screw her.
谁管她
You watch it, boy.
你说话小心点 小子
Say what you want,
不管你想怎么说
but your mom's paying for your school.
都是你母亲在帮你付学费
All your living expenses,
这里的生活费
she's the one paying for your room and board every month.
跟寄宿费每个月也都是你母亲支付的
She's been protecting you.
她一直在保护你啊
Do you understand?
你明白吗？
-So just give her some peace of mind. -Okay.
-所以你现在要让妈妈放心 -好啦
-Whatever, I'm done. -Hey.
-随便啦 我受够了 -喂
Akira!
阿晶！
You should take a bandanna.
你应该带块头巾
Good morning.
早上好
Didn't she mess with a student?
她是不是对学生出手了？
You wouldn't think it from looking at her!
真是人不可貌相！
TEACHER'S LOUNGE
（教职员室）
Good morning.
早上好
Huh?
嗯？
Akira, you're gonna be late.
阿晶 你会迟到喔
You're not missing school today--
今天你一定要去学校…
Huh?
嗯？
He what?
阿晶怎么了？
Here.
你看
THANKS FOR EVERYTHING
（感谢你们一直以来的照顾）
What is this?
怎么回事？
GOODBYE. AKIRA.
（再见 晶）
-Where did Akira go? -Please calm down.
-阿晶去哪了？ -你先冷静
I'm going to call around, okay?
我先去联络其他人 好吗？
Don't tell me he…
他该不会…
Ms. Suenaga.
末永老师
You have a visitor.
外面有访客找你
Iwasaki.
岩崎同学
I came here to punch you.
我是来狠揍老师一顿的
Just kidding.
开玩笑的
Is Kuroiwa here now?
黑岩他在这里吗？
Huh? Why?
嗯？为什么？
-Of course not-- -Really?
-当然没有… -真的？
Really.
真的
What? Why?
什么？为什么？
What happened?
发生什么事了？
Kuroiwa disappeared.
黑岩不见了
His mom said he left a note and vanished.
他妈妈说他留下字条后就消失了
She gave us a call.
她也联络了我们
He probably ran away.
他可能是离家出走
-Since when? -I don't know.
-几时的事？ -我不知道
Yesterday or today.
昨天或今天吧
His mom was asking everyone.
他妈妈正在到处找人
I was sure he'd be here.
可是我认为他肯定在这里
I don't know, I haven't seen him.
我不知道 我没见到他
Where did he go?
他到底去哪了？
That idiot.
那个笨蛋
I got better things to do.
我才没空理他
He's not even that hot.
少得意了 其实也没有很帅
And started high school basically a stalker.
上高中就变得跟踪狂似的
It's okay if you don't know where he is. It's not your problem.
不知道就算了 这件事跟你无关
Goodbye.
再见
INCIDENT / ACCIDENT
（事件 事故）
RUN AWAY
（离家出走）
Komiya Dai-Ichi Elementary.
是 这里是小宫第一小学
Hello?
喂？
Ms. Suenaga?
老师？
Um, can you hear me?
嗯 你听得到我的声音吗？
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
Where are you?
你在哪里？
Iwasaki came by.
刚才岩崎同学来过了
Everyone's worried.
大家都很担心你
Tell me where you are.
告诉我 你现在人在哪
I wanted to apologize.
我想向你道歉
-Kuroiwa! -I'm sorry for the other day.
-黑岩同学！ -上次真是对不起
For just showing up and lashing out.
擅自跑去找你大放厥词
It's fine.
没关系
Everything you said was true.
毕竟你说的都是事实
I loved your lessons.
我很喜欢上你的课
Your writing on the chalkboard,
不管是黑板上的字
the lilt in your voice…
还是你教学时的嗓音…
I still remember them now.
我现在仍然记得
Welcome Rain on a Spring Night.
《春夜喜雨》
"The good rain knows its season."
“好雨知时节
When spring arrives, it brings life.
当春乃发生”
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
Good luck.
你要加油
Kuroiwa.
黑岩同学
Please tell me where you are right now.
拜托你告诉我 你到底在哪里？
I just wanted to say that one last thing.
我只是想在最后跟你说这些话
Last?
最后？
The ferry for Yamaejima is now allowing all cars to board.
前往山江岛的渡轮 现在允许所有车辆上船
Goodbye, Ms. Suenaga.
再见了 老师
Kuroiwa, wait!
黑岩同学 等等！
Yamaejima?
山江岛？
YAMAEJIMA FERRY
（山江岛 渡轮）
Ms. Suenaga.
末永老师
Are you ready to leave? It's getting late.
要走了吗？已经很晚了
Ms. Suenaga!
末永老师！
We should talk.
我们应该谈谈
Okay.
好
Could you come with me?
你愿意跟我走吗？
Huh?
嗯？
Instead of staying here,
与其待在这里
come with me.
不如跟我走吧
Actually,
其实
I have to quit the school.
我要辞职了
My father fell ill.
我父亲病倒了
I'm taking over his business.
我要回去继承老家的餐厅
Then
那么
you won't teach again?
你不当老师了吗？
So,
所以
come with me.
跟我一起
Would you
要不要
leave this town with me?
跟我一起离开这里？
I figured it was a long shot.
果然是不可能吧
You have someone you want to see, don't you?
你有想见的人吧？
I've fallen in love with you.
我喜欢上老师了
I want you to fall in love with me too.
我希望老师也能喜欢上我
I'll also go to IKEA.
我还要去宜家
-Then I'll go with you. -No.
-那我也一起去 -不行
Ms. Suenaga! Thank you!
老师！谢谢！
I don't care what anyone says.
我不在意别人怎么说
I love you.
我喜欢老师
I'll be an adult soon!
我很快会成为大人！
Hijiri!
小圣！
I'm still…
我还是…
the same as on that day.
那个时候的我
You should go.
快去吧
It's okay.
没关系
Thank you.
谢谢你
The ferry to Yamaejima is leaving soon.
前往山江岛的渡轮即将出航
Kuroiwa!
黑岩同学！
Ms. Suenaga.
老师
-The two of them ran off together? -Do you understand?
-他们两人一起私奔了？ -你明白吗？
This could be a crime!
这可是犯罪啊！
-Dad? -Akira.
-你是我爸 对吧？ -阿晶
I don't know anymore.
我不知道该怎么办了
What can I do to forget you?
到底该怎样才能忘记你？
Subtitle translation by: Zensho Yamamoto
字幕翻译：高文欣